Guide to the Bayrd Still Papers MC.44
New York University Archives
- Series II: Research, Committees, Talks, Reviews, Still's Articles, 1935-1977
  - Subseries D: NYU Committees, 1956-1971
    - Committee to nominate candidates for Dean of Graduate School, Arts and Science, February - May 1964 (Box 18, Folder 10)
    - Committee to Select Dean of Graduate School, 1970-1971 (Box 18, Folder 11)
  - Subseries E: Talks, Reviews, 1938-1965
    Subseries E includes files on Still's talks, as well as press and reviews, some of which relate to Still's own publications.
    - M.V.H.A., Membership Committee, 1957-1959 (Box 18, Folder 12)
    - Gettysburg College, Civil War Conference, Nov. 17, 18, 19, 1958, 1957-1958 (Box 18, Folder 13)
    - "Urban Drift," Draft, not published; item for DICTIONARY OF AMERICAN HISTORY, 1938 (Box 18, Folder 14)
    - Speech, "City in American History," Duke University, Apr. 18, 1952 (Box 18, Folder 15)
    - MILWAUKEE: HISTORY OF A CITY, 1st ed.: Inception, Reviews, Letters, Promotion, 1938-1950 (Box 18, Folder 16)
    - MILWAUKEE: HISTORY OF A CITY, 2nd ed.: Correspondence, Reviews, 1964-1965 (Box 19, Folder 1)
      3 1142 04225064 0
    - MIRROR FOR GOTHAM: Reviews, Letters, etc., 1957-1959 (Box 19, Folder 2)
    - MIRROR FOR GOTHAM: Bibliography, undated (Box 19, Folder 3)
    - "Comment," Local History Session, A.H.A., Dec. 31, 1957 (Box 19, Folder 4)
    - Paper, "The City and the Arts, 1860-1910," Archives of American Art Conference, Winterthur Museum, Apr. 7, 1962 (Box 19, Folder 5)
    - "Comment," M.V.H.A., Session, Apr. 14, 1949 (Box 19, Folder 6)
    - "Joseph Weydemeyer, Marxian Socialist," session on forty-eighters, A.H.A., December, 1948, 1948-1949 (Box 19, Folder 7)
    - "Comment," M.V.H.A., Session, May 3, 1963 (Box 19, Folder 8)
    - Comment, "Southern Cities," M.V.H.A., Apr. 23, 1965 (Box 19, Folder 9)
    - Speech, "New York's Mayoralty -- Formative Years," New-York Historical Society, Nov. 13, 1962 (Box 19, Folder 10)
    - Speeches on "Personality of New York City" at Teachers College, Columbia; New York Folklore Society; New-York Historical Society; New York Guild for the Jewish Blind, 1959-1961 (Box 19, Folder 11)
    - WNYC Talk, "New York a Century Ago", 1965 (Box 19, Folder 12)
  - Subseries F: Partial Collection of Articles in Historical Journals, 1935-1977
    Subseries F contains Still's own publications, a group that he titled: "Partial Collection of Articles in Historical Journals".
    - "Evidences of the Higher Life on the Frontier, as Illustrated in the History of Cultural Matters in Chicago, 1830-1850," JOURNAL OF THE ILLINOIS HISTORICAL SOCIETY, XXVIII, 81-99, July 1935 (Box 20, Folder 1)
      3 1142 04225065 7
    - "California's First Constitution: A Reflection of the Political Philosophy of the Frontier," PACIFIC HISTORICAL REVIEW, IV, 221-34, September 1935 (Box 20, Folder 2)
    - "State-Making in Wisconsin, 1846-48: An Illustration of the Statehood Process," WISCONSIN MAGAZINE OF HISTORY, XX, 34-49, September 1936 (Box 20, Folder 3)
    - "An Interpretation of the Statehood Process, 1800-1850," MISSISSIPPI VALLEY HISTORICAL REVIEW, XXIII, 189-204, September 1936 (Box 20, Folder 4)
    - "The Growth of Milwaukee as Recorded by Contemporaries," WISCONSIN MAGAZINE OF HISTORY, XXI, 262-300, March 1938 (Box 20, Folder 5)
    - "The Abner Morse Diary: River Falls, 1859-61," ed. with William Herrmann, WISCONSIN MAGAZINE OF HISTORY, XXII, 427- 34 (June 1939); XXIII, 62-88 (September 1939) (Box 20, Folder 6)
    - "Milwaukee, 1870-1900: The Emergence of a Metropolis," WISCONSIN MAGAZINE OF HISTORY, XXIII, 138-62, December, 1939 (Box 21, Folder 1)
      3 1142 04225073 1
    - "To The West on Business in 1804: An Account...of James Ford's Trip to Kentucky in 1804," PENNSYLVANIA MAGAZINE OF HISTORY AND BIOGRAPHY, LXIV, 1940 (Box 21, Folder 2)
    - "Patterns of Mid-Nineteenth Century Urbanization in the Middle West," MISSISSIPPI VALLEY HISTORICAL REVIEW, XXVIII, 187-206, September 1941 (Box 21, Folder 3)
    - "The Development of Milwaukee in the Early Metropolitan Period," WISCONSIN MAGAZINE OF HISTORY, XXV, 297-307, March 1942 (Box 21, Folder 4)
    - "Observations of Henry Barnard on the West and South of the 1840's," JOURNAL OF SOUTHERN HISTORY, VIII, 247-58, May 1942 (Box 21, Folder 5)
    - "The Personality of New York City," NEW YORK FOLKLORE QUARTERLY, XIV, 83-92, Summer 1958 (Box 21, Folder 6)
    - "The Essence of New York City," NEW-YORK HISTORICAL SOCIETY QUARTERLY, XLIII, 401-423, October 1959 (Box 21, Folder 7)
    - "New York City in 1824: A Newly Discovered Description," NEW-YORK HISTORICAL SOCIETY QUARTERLY, XLVI, 137-169, April 1962 (Box 22, Folder 1)
      3 1142 04225072 3
    - "The History of the City in American Life, AMERICAN REVIEW, II, 20-37, May 1962 (Box 22, Folder 2)
    - "New York's Mayoralty: the Formative Years," NEW-YORK HISTORICAL SOCIETY QUARTERLY, XLVII, 239-55, July 1963 (Box 22, Folder 3)
    - "The Teaching of American Urban History," [with Diana Klebanow], JOURNAL OF AMERICAN HISTORY, LV, 34-43, March 1969 (Box 22, Folder 4)
    - "Milwaukee in 1836 and 1849: A Contemporary Description," WISCONSIN MAGAZINE OF HISTORY, LIII, 294-97, Summer 1970 (Box 22, Folder 5)
    - "Comments," in William C. Wright, ed., URBAN NEW JERSEY SINCE 1870, Papers Presented at the Sixth Annual New Jersey History Symposium--1974 (Trenton New Jersey Historical Commission, 1975), 78-82. (Box 22, Folder 6)
    - "Milwaukee Revisited: A Review Article," WISCONSIN MAGAZINE OF HISTORY, LX, 330-33. 8 Draft, "State Constitutions," Summer 1977 (Box 22, Folder 7)
    - Draft, "State Constitutions", undated (Box 22, Folder 8)
    - "Evidences of the 'Higher Life' on the Frontier as Illustrated in the History of Cultural Matters in Chicago, 1830-1850," JOURNAL OF THE ILLINOIS STATE HISTORICAL SOCIETY vol. XXVIII no. 2, 1935 July (Box 64, Folder 3)
    - "An Interpretation of the Statehood Process, 1800 to 1850," MISSISSIPPI VALLEY HISTORICAL REVIEW vol. XXIII no. 2, 1936 September (Box 64, Folder 4)
    - "To the West on Business in 1804", 1940 January (Box 64, Folder 5)
    - "Patterns of Mid-Nineteenth Century Urbanization in the Middle West," MISSISSIPPI VALLEY HISTORICAL REVIEW vol. XXVIII no. 2, 1941 September (Box 64, Folder 6)
    - "The Personality of New York City," NEW YORK FOLKLORE QUARTERLY vol. XIV no. 2, 1958 (Box 64, Folder 7)
    - "The City and the Arts, 1860-1910," in Archives of American Art, A REPORT ON CONFERENCE IV: NEEDS AND OPPORTUNITIES FOR RE-EVALUATION IN THE ARTS IN AMERICA, 1860-1910, 1962, April 6-7 (Box 64, Folder 8)
    - "Milwaukee in 1836 and 1849: A Contemporary Description," WISCONSIN MAGAZINE OF HISTORY vol. 53 no. 4, 1970 (Box 64, Folder 9)
- Series III: NYC Research, 1650-1989
  Series III contains materials related to Bayrd Still's research interest in New York City and urban history.
  - Subseries A: Landmarks
    Subseries A: Landmarks contains information on New York City landmarks.
    - Landmarks in New York City, 1962-1965 (Box 23, Folder 1)
      3 1142 04225071 5
    - Reed, Henry H., Walking Tours - New York City, 1958-1960 (Box 23, Folder 2)
    - Landmarks Preservation Commission: Bill; Calendar, Vol. 1, No. 1; Clippings, 1962-1966 (Box 23, Folder 3)
    - Fraunces Tavern - Reconstruction, 1965 (Box 23, Folder 4)
    - Huxtable, Ada L., Preservation in New York, 1962 (Box 23, Folder 5)
    - Population, Major Cities, 1854, 1860, 1870, 1950 (Box 23, Folder 6)
    - Skeletons in Washington Square Park, 1965 (Box 23, Folder 7)
    - Hangings in what is now Washington Square Park, 1969 (Box 23, Folder 8)
    - Burial Ground in Manhattan - Research Notes, undated (Box 23, Folder 9)
    - Greenwich Village Historic District Designation Report, Volume I, 1969 (Box 65, Folder 1)
    - Greenwich Village Historic District Designation Report, Volume II, 1969 (Box 65, Folder 2)
  - Subseries B: Research on NYC
    - Noteworthy Commentary on Cities (General), undated (Box 23, Folder 10)
    - Cities (General), Contemporary Description of, 1789 through 1869, undated (Box 23, Folder 11)
    - Cities (General), Contemporary Description of, 1870's, undated (Box 23, Folder 12)
    - Cities (General), Contemporary Description of, 1880's, undated (Box 23, Folder 13)
    - Cities (General), Contemporary Description of, 1890's, undated (Box 23, Folder 14)
    - Cities (General), Contemporary Description of, since 1900, undated (Box 24, Folder 1)
      3 1142 04225070 7
    - New York City, Miscellaneous Description of, undated (Box 24, Folder 2)
    - New York City, Contemporary Description of, 1524 through 1769, undated (Box 24, Folder 3)
    - New York City, Contemporary Description of, 1772 through 1776, undated (Box 24, Folder 4)
    - New York City, Contemporary Description of, 1777 through 1788, undated (Box 24, Folder 5)
    - New York City, Contemporary Description of, 1789 through 1815, undated (Box 24, Folder 6)
    - New York City, Contemporary Description of, 1816 through 1827, undated (Box 24, Folder 7)
    - New York City, Contemporary Description of, 1828 through 1836, undated (Box 25, Folder 1)
      3 1142 04225069 9
    - The Great Metropolis, 1845, undated (Box 25, Folder 2)
    - New York City, Contemporary Description of, 1837 through 1849, undated (Box 25, Folder 3)
    - New York City, Contemporary Description of, 1850 through 1854, undated (Box 25, Folder 4)
    - New York City, Contemporary Description of, 1855 through 1869, undated (Box 26, Folder 1)
      3 1142 04225068 1
    - New York City, Contemporary Description of, 1870 through 1889, undated (Box 26, Folder 2)
    - New York City, Contemporary Description of, 1890 through 1913, undated (Box 26, Folder 3)
    - New York City, Contemporary Description of, 1914 through 1934, undated (Box 26, Folder 4)
    - New York City, Contemporary Description of, 1935 through 1953, undated (Box 27, Folder 1)
      3 1142 04225067 3
    - New York City, Description by Bayrd Still, for COLLIER'S ENCYCLOPEDIA, 1975 (Box 27, Folder 2)
    - Brooklyn Rediscovery, 1979-1983 (Box 27, Folder 3)
    - Molinari, Gustave de, LETTRES SUR LES ETATS-UNIS (Paris, 1876). Biography and bibliography., undated (Box 27, Folder 4)
    - Molinari, Translation by Bayrd Still of excerpts on Philadelphia, undated (Box 27, Folder 5)
    - Molinari, Translation by Bayrd Still of excerpts on Baltimore and Washington, undated (Box 27, Folder 6)
    - Molinari, Translation by Bayrd Still of excerpts on Charleston, Savannah, Augusta, Atlanta, New Orleans, undated (Box 27, Folder 7)
    - Molinari, Translation by Bayrd Still of excerpts on St. Louis, 1976 (Box 27, Folder 8)
    - Molinari, Translation by Bayrd Still of excerpts on Chicago, undated (Box 27, Folder 9)
    - Molinari, Translation by Bayrd Still of excerpts on Boston, undated (Box 27, Folder 10)
    - Molinari, Translation by Bayrd Still of excerpts from his "Summary Reflections on American Society", undated (Box 27, Folder 11)
    - Molinari, Itinerary, undated (Box 27, Folder 12)
    - Chinese in New York, Image of, 1870-1920 Term Paper of Keith Carpenter, 1972 (Box 27, Folder 13)
    - Interpretations and Ideas, undated (Box 27, Folder 14)
    - Clippings on Image of City, 1970-1975 (Box 27, Folder 15)
    - Molinari, Misc., 1976 (Box 27, Folder 16)
    - Traveler-Commentators, Nature of, Reliability, etc., undated (Box 28, Folder 1)
      3 1142 04225066 5
    - Articles on Municipal Affairs, 1853 to 1897, reflecting increasing interest in city, undated (Box 28, Folder 2)
    - Donaldson, Scott, "City and Country: Marriage Proposals" (1968) (Box 28, Folder 3)
    - True, Dr. A. C., "Solidarity of Town and Farm" (1897), undated (Box 28, Folder 4)
    - Kendall, J. C., THE GROWTH OF NEW YORK (1865). Sense of "metropolism", undated (Box 28, Folder 5)
    - Kaul, A. N., THE AMERICAN VISION ...(19th century fiction), 1963 (Box 28, Folder 6)
    - Poetry and the American City (Lorca, Ginsberg, Eliot, Crane), undated (Box 28, Folder 7)
    - Rowe, Leo S., "American Political Ideas and...City...", undated (Box 28, Folder 8)
    - Booth, Michael R., "The Metropolis on Stage", 1973 (Box 28, Folder 9)
    - Milwaukee, Miscellaneous Material, undated (Box 28, Folder 10)
    - Gowans, Alan, "Rural Myth and Urban Fact in the American Heritage", 1965 (Box 28, Folder 11)
    - Hotels, 1850 to 1870, undated (Box 28, Folder 12)
    - Apartment Houses: early 1870's, undated (Box 28, Folder 13)
    - City Guide Books, 1855 to 1870, undated (Box 28, Folder 14)
    - Briggs, Asa, Attitudes toward cities, England and America, undated (Box 28, Folder 15)
    - Books dealing with urban themes, miscellaneous, undated (Box 28, Folder 16)
    - Gilchrist, David, ed. GROWTH OF SEAPORT CITIES, 1790-1825, undated (Box 28, Folder 17)
    - Negroes in New York City in 1867 as Described in NEW YORK WORLD, Mar. 16, 1867, undated (Box 28, Folder 18)
    - Chalmers, Leonard, "Fernando Wood and Tammany Hall: The First Phase," THE NEW-YORK HISTORICAL SOCIETY QUARTERLY, vol. LII no. 4, 1968 October (Box 65, Folder 3)
    - Mohl, Raymond A., "The Humane Society and Urban Reform in Early New York, 1787-1831," THE NEW-YORK HISTORICAL SOCIETY QUARTERLY vol. LIV no. 1, 1970 January (Box 65, Folder 4)
    - Mohl, Raymond A., "Humanitarianism in the Pre-Industrial City: The New York Society for the Prevention of Pauperism, 1817-1823," THE JOURNAL OF AMERICAN HISTORY vol. LVII no. 3, 1970 December (Box 65, Folder 5)
    - Carosso, Vincent, "Washington and Wall Street: The New Deal and Investment Bankers, 1933-1940," THE BUSINESS HISTORY REVIEW vol. XLIV no. 4, 1970 Winter (Box 65, Folder 6)
    - Cohen, Ira, "The Auction System in the Port of New York, 1817-1837," THE BUSINESS HISTORY REVIEW vol. LXV no. 4, 1971 Winter (Box 65, Folder 7)
    - Chalmers, Leonard, "The Crucial Test of La Guardia's First Hundred Days: The Emergency Economy Bill," THE NEW-YORK HISTORICAL SOCIETY QUARTERLY vol. LVII no. 3, 1973 July (Box 65, Folder 8)
    - "Ebony Patriots: Participation of Blacks in Battles of the American Revolution in the New York City Area 1776-1779", 1976 (Box 65, Folder 9)
    - Chalmers, Leonard, "Fiorello La Guardia, Paterfamilias at City Hall: An Appraisal", undated (Box 65, Folder 10)
    - Mohl, Raymond A., "The Urban Missionary Movement in New York City, 1800-1825," JOURNAL OF RELIGIOUS HISTORY, undated (Box 65, Folder 11)
  - Subseries C: Sources about Urbanism and Urban Development
    Subseries C: Sources about Urbanism and Urban Development contains urban history research material that includes some original material, some published sources, and some of Still's own translations of published material. Materials contain published and unpublished sources about urbanism and urban development in the United States from the 17th century to the 20th century.
    - City in American Thought -- General, 1948-1949 (Box 29, Folder 1)
      3 1142 04225081 4
    - [Johnson, Edward], WONDER-WORKING PROVIDENCE, ca. 1650, undated (Box 29, Folder 2)
    - Maverick, Samuel, Description of New England Towns, ca. 1660, undated (Box 29, Folder 3)
    - Josselyn, John, AN ACCOUNT OF TWO VOYAGES TO NEW-ENGLAND, 1663, undated (Box 29, Folder 4)
    - Denton, Daniel, A BRIEF DESCRIPTION OF NEW-YORK, 1670, undated (Box 29, Folder 5)
    - Blome, Richard, Description of New-York, 1672, undated (Box 29, Folder 6)
    - Mathews, Maurice (?), Description of Charlestowne, 1680, undated (Box 29, Folder 7)
    - Penn, William, Proposal for city development in Pennsylvania, 1681, undated (Box 29, Folder 8)
    - Penn, William, Description of Philadelphia, as of 1684, undated (Box 29, Folder 9)
    - Letters describing Philadelphia, ca. 1691, undated (Box 29, Folder 10)
    - Bullivant, Dr. Benjamin, Description of New-York, 1697, undated (Box 29, Folder 11)
    - Virginia, account of, deploring absence of towns, 1697(?), undated (Box 29, Folder 12)
    - [Francis Makemie], A PLAIN & FRIENDLY PERSWASIVE TO THE INHABITANTS OF VIRGINIA & MARYLAND FOR PROMOTING TOWNS & COHABITATION, undated (Box 29, Folder 13)
    - Boston Records re Irish, Negroes, Indians, 1717-1736, undated (Box 29, Folder 14)
    - Jones, Hugh, THE PRESENT STATE OF VIRGINIA, 1724, undated (Box 29, Folder 15)
    - Comer, John, Diary, Letter from Boston, 1729, undated (Box 29, Folder 16)
    - New York City Ordinances, 1731, undated (Box 29, Folder 17)
    - Franklin, Benjamin, Clubs, Urban Services, 1731, 1736, undated (Box 29, Folder 18)
    - Pharmacy Advertisement in German, 1734, undated (Box 29, Folder 19)
    - New York City Politics, Cosby, Zenger, undated (Box 29, Folder 20)
    - Moore, Francis, Savannah, 1736, undated (Box 29, Folder 21)
    - Edwards, Geo. W., "New York City Politics before the American Revolution" (1921), undated (Box 29, Folder 22)
    - Hamilton, Dr. Alexander, Description of New York, Boston, Philadelphia, 1744, 1948 (Box 29, Folder 23)
    - Kalm, Peter, Philadelphia, 1748, 1964 (Box 29, Folder 24)
    - Smith, William, Jr. Anti-urban View in INDEPENDENT REFLECTOR, 1753, undated (Box 29, Folder 25)
    - Advertisements, NEW-YORK GAZETTE, 1753/1754, undated (Box 29, Folder 26)
    - Argument for Towns, NEW-YORK GAZETTE, Mar. 19, 1753, undated (Box 29, Folder 27)
    - Dogs in New York, INDEPENDENT REFLECTOR, Jan. 18, 1753, 1963 (Box 29, Folder 28)
    - Fire-fighting in New York, in INDEPENDENT REFLECTOR, Jan. 11, 1753, 1963 (Box 29, Folder 29)
    - "Defense of New York against the Slanders of New England," Feb. 28, 1756, undated (Box 29, Folder 30)
    - Adams, John, DIARY AND AUTOBIOGRAPHY, 1758-1774, undated (Box 29, Folder 31)
    - Predictions of Urban Growth, 1758-1773, undated (Box 29, Folder 32)
    - Gordon, Lord Adam, JOURNAL, 1764, 1765, undated (Box 29, Folder 33)
    - Boyle, John, JOURNAL, 1765-1773, 1930 (Box 29, Folder 34)
    - Quincy, Josiah, Jr., JOURNAL, 1773, undated (Box 29, Folder 35)
    - Adams, John, Attitudes toward cities, ca. 1775, undated (Box 29, Folder 36)
    - Anonymous Frenchman, re Charleston and Philadelphia, 1777, 1959 (Box 29, Folder 37)
    - Smyth, J. F. D., A TOUR IN THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA, ca. 1783, undated (Box 29, Folder 38)
    - Jefferson, Thomas, re Cities, 1785-1823, undated (Box 29, Folder 39)
    - Cities Compared, 1786, undated (Box 29, Folder 40)
    - Coxe, Tench, City Growth, 1789, 1791, undated (Box 29, Folder 41)
    - Rubin, Julius, "Urban Growth and Regional Development," 1790-1825, 1967 (Box 29, Folder 42)
    - L'Enfant, Pierre, Vision of Capital City, 1791, 1792, 1929 (Box 29, Folder 43)
    - American City in Drama, 1787-1860, 1958 (Box 29, Folder 44)
    - Carey, Mathew, Yellow Fever, Philadelphia, 1793, undated (Box 29, Folder 45)
    - Cooper, Thomas, American Towns, 1793, 1794, undated (Box 29, Folder 46)
    - Baltimore, 1795, ff, undated (Box 29, Folder 47)
    - Carey, Mathew, CAREY'S AMERICAN POCKET ATLAS, 1796, undated (Box 29, Folder 48)
    - Bulow, A. H. D. von, New York- Philadelphia Rivalry, 1796, undated (Box 29, Folder 49)
    - Poem on Acquisition of Louisiana, 1804, 1971 (Box 29, Folder 50)
    - Description of New York by Philadelphian, 1806, undated (Box 29, Folder 51)
    - Tucker, George, ESSAYS, 1813, undated (Box 29, Folder 52)
    - Drake, Daniel, NATURAL AND STATISTICAL VIEW, OR PICTURE OF CINCINNATI, 1815, undated (Box 29, Folder 53)
    - Flower, George, History of English Settlement in Illinois, 1817, 1818, undated (Box 29, Folder 54)
    - Society for the Prevention of Pauperism in the City of New-York, Reports, 1818, 1819, undated (Box 29, Folder 55)
    - Hecke, J. V., REISE DURCH DIE VEREINIGTEN STAATEN, 1818, 1819, undated (Box 30, Folder 1)
      3 1142 04225080 6
    - Flint, James, Lexington, Ky., 1818, undated (Box 30, Folder 2)
    - Tudor, William, LETTERS ON THE EASTERN STATES, 1819, undated (Box 30, Folder 3)
    - Trumbull, H., WESTERN EMIGRATION, 1819(?), undated (Box 30, Folder 4)
    - Holmes, Isaac, Chapter on Cities and Towns in AN ACCOUNT OF THE UNITED STATES OF AMERICA, 1819-1822, undated (Box 30, Folder 5)
    - Cooper, Thomas, LECTURES ON THE ELEMENTS OF POLITICAL ECONOMY, 1826, undated (Box 30, Folder 6)
    - City Life and Women's Health, 1826, undated (Box 30, Folder 7)
    - Cooper, J. Fenimore, Comparative Comment on Cities, 1826, 1827, undated (Box 30, Folder 8)
    - Newspaper comment n new types coming into city government, 1827, undated (Box 30, Folder 9)
    - Communication and Impact of City, 1827, undated (Box 30, Folder 10)
    - WESTERN MONTHLY REVIEW, Anti-urban Comment, 1827, undated (Box 30, Folder 11)
    - Murat, Achille, AMERICA AND THE AMERICANS, 1827-30(?), undated (Box 30, Folder 12)
    - WESTERN MONTHLY REVIEW, Anti-urban view, 1828, undated (Box 30, Folder 13)
    - Sealsfield, Charles, Cincinnati, 1828, undated (Box 30, Folder 14)
    - Trollope, Frances, Cincinnati, Cincinnati, 1828-1830, undated (Box 30, Folder 15)
    - New York Contrasted with Other Cities, Nov. 10, 1829, undated (Box 30, Folder 16)
    - Urbanism in Ohio, 1829, undated (Box 30, Folder 17)
    - Emerson, Ralph W. and the American City, 1829-1867, undated (Box 30, Folder 18)
    - LONG ISLAND STAR, Brooklyn Village, 1830, 1969 (Box 30, Folder 19)
    - Expediency of having University in New York City views of Henry Dwight and George Bancroft, 1830, undated (Box 30, Folder 20)
    - Cemeteries, Rural type, 1831-1870, undated (Box 30, Folder 21)
    - Sedgwick, Catherine M., CLARENCE (a novel), 1830, revised 1849, New York setting, undated (Box 30, Folder 22)
    - Pro-urban View, 1830-1832, undated (Box 30, Folder 23)
    - Tocqueville, Alexis de, 1831, 1832, Cities as dangerous, undated (Box 30, Folder 24)
    - City Growth, 1832; in West, 1833, 1835, undated (Box 30, Folder 25)
    - Dwight, Timothy, THINGS AS THEY ARE. Reflects urban-rural tension; New York is like a "watch-maker's shop", undated (Box 30, Folder 26)
    - Flint, Timothy, Journey from Cincinnati to Boston; cities observed, 1833, undated (Box 30, Folder 27)
    - Chevalier, Michael, LETTERS ON NORTH AMERICA, 1833-1835, 1961 (Box 30, Folder 28)
    - Pittsburgh observed, 1833, 1846, undated (Box 30, Folder 29)
    - Rural Enjoyment, 1833, undated (Box 30, Folder 30)
    - Drake, Daniel, DISCOURSE, Cities in growth of West, 1834, undated (Box 30, Folder 31)
    - Power, Tyrone, Cities in West, 1834, undated (Box 30, Folder 32)
    - Hoffman, C. F., Cities in West; Chicago, 1834, undated (Box 30, Folder 33)
    - Lieber, Francis, Immigration, 1834, undated (Box 30, Folder 34)
    - WESTERN MONTHLY MAGAZINE, 1834, 1835, undated (Box 30, Folder 35)
    - Cooper, J. Fenimore, HOME AS FOUND, 1834, 1835, undated (Box 30, Folder 36)
    - KNICKERBOCKER, 1835-1838, Buffalo described, undated (Box 30, Folder 37)
    - Walker, James B., Pioneer Life in in the...Cities of the West, 1835, ff., undated (Box 30, Folder 38)
    - Abundance of America theme, Immigrant Letter; Peck's NEW GUIDE FOR EMIGRANTS TO THE WEST, 1837, undated (Box 30, Folder 39)
    - "American Society," KNICKERBOCKER, 1836. On city and country., undated (Box 30, Folder 40)
    - "God made the country...man the town," KNICKERBOCKER, 1836, undated (Box 30, Folder 41)
    - "Town and country," KNICKERBOCKER, 1836, undated (Box 30, Folder 42)
    - Cities in West (Rochester) in Knickerbocker IX, 1837, undated (Box 30, Folder 43)
    - Marry at, Frederick, DIARY, City rivalry and antagonism, 1837, undated (Box 30, Folder 44)
    - Sedgwick, Catherine M., Anti-city View, 1837, undated (Box 30, Folder 45)
    - City pro and con, 1840's and 1850's, undated (Box 30, Folder 46)
    - [Charles F. Briggs], ADVENTURES OF HARRY FRANCO (novel), Life in New York, undated (Box 30, Folder 47)
    - Tucker, Geo., PROGRESS of US., Chapter on Cities and Towns, 1843, undated (Box 30, Folder 48)
    - PRAIRIE FARMER, 1843-1873, Rural Rural and urban living, 1957 (Box 30, Folder 49)